There was a story that you mentioned in
your book where where there was a Middle
Eastern intelligence guy that you went
to his house. [laughter]
>> That story I am so proud of that
operation and I wish that it had been my
idea. It was not my idea.
>> I had a mentor at the CIA. He was an old
man. He was a retiree. His name was Gus
Avricatus. He became famous and they
even made a movie about him, Charlie
Wilson's War, in which he's played by
Philip Seymour Hoffman.
>> So, I told Gust, I said, "Listen,
this this enemy country, the CIA won't
allow me to say what country it is, but
it's kind of obvious. this enemy
country. They're getting a new
intelligence service uh representative
and I want to bump into him, but this is
not a guy who's going to be at a
diplomatic cocktail party.
>> How do I get to him? So Gus gave me this
idea. I I was much younger at the time.
I was 35 years old. My hair was darker.
My my I grew a beard and it was dark.
Now I'm all gray. But I put some books
in a book bag. I went to his house. I
saw his car was on the street. And with
my book bag, I broke the side view
mirror off of his car. So I picked it
up. I went to the next door neighbor
just to provide cover for myself. And I
said to the woman, "Is this your car?"
She said, "No, it's the man next door.
He doesn't speak Greek." So I went to
his house. I knocked on the door and I
saidto,
"I'm so sorry, sir, but the lady next
door told me that this is your car and I
broke the I said, "I'm so clumsy." He
says, "Wait, wait a minute. Wait a
minute. I don't speak I don't speak
Greek." I said, "Oh, you speak English?"
"I speak English." I said, "I'm so
sorry. I I I was clumsy and I wasn't
paying attention to where I was going
and and I broke the mirror off your car
and the lady next door told me that it
was your car and I want to say I'm sorry
and I want to pay for it. He's like,
"Oh, you're so clumsy. What's wrong with
you? You could you couldn't see how
close you were." I said, "I I'm so
sorry. I was just not paying attention.
It's all my fault. I want to pay for
it." In the meantime,
well, I said to him, I said, "Uh, I
said, "Your English, you have an accent.
can you tell me where you're from? And
he told me from this Middle East
country. And I said, I'm from the United
States. I said, oh, I wish our countries
could be friends again. Maybe someday.
And he's just like,
and I see his little daughter. She
looked to be about four years old. She's
playing on the floor of the living room.
And I I said to him, "May I have a glass
of water?" Knowing that culturally he
had to give it to me.
>> Yeah. And he says,"Wait right here."
So, uh, I walked into the house and I
said to his daughter, I got down on my
knee and I said, "Uh, uh, shmink."
And she tells me her name and I said,
"How old are you?" And she says, "She's
four." And he comes in, he's holding the
water. And he says, "What exactly do you
want from me?"
>> He knows that, you know.
>> Oh, 100%. He's a professional. He's not
an idiot. So I said, 'Look,
I'm from the CIA in Washington. I know
exactly who you are and what you're
doing here. You have one chance to be on
the side of the good guys. And I took
out my business card and I said, "This
is my real name. The phone rings on my
desk at the American embassy. You have
until 10:00 tomorrow morning to call me.
You can be on the side of the good guys
or you can go down with your leader."
and I put it down on it the table and he
said to me, "I admire your courage in
approaching me. Very inventive."
He said, "But I hate that you did it in
my own home. You can leave now." So I
said, "10 tomorrow morning." And I
walked out. The next morning,
everybody's gathered around my desk
>> waiting for the phone call.
>> Waiting everybody.
[laughter] And then the phone rings.
>> Does it?
>> Uhhuh. And he said, "What do you want
from me?" And I said, "Meet me in the
Hilton Hotel coffee shop in two hours
and don't bring a weapon."
So we had we our security people were
literally at every table.
>> Wow.
>> Of the Hilton coffee shop. Everybody's
armed. I have a bulletproof vest on
under my suit. And he comes and I tell
him, "Have a seat." And he said, "So,
how does this play out?" And I said,
"I want access to your code room and I
want all your weapons."
And he said, "Do you know how hard that
is?" And I said, "Yes, I also know how
important you are and I know that of
anybody in the embassy besides the
ambassador, you have the access." And he
said, "What do I get in return?" I said,
"Well, number one, you get to live.
Number two, I can make you rich beyond
your wildest dreams.
So, what is it? What do you want? And we
negotiated a deal. And we made a plan.
We took the codes. The weapons were
buried in a bunker outside the embassy
underground. We went in the middle of
the night. Six guys with shovels. We
took all the weapons
and then he disappeared.
Is there a witness protection program in
gender? Is that is that a is that a
really
>> Yes. The last time I heard about him, it
was it was several years after I left
the uh left the CIA and I ran into a
former colleague and I said, "How's
Steve?" Steve was what we just called
him. We didn't use his Arabic name. We
just made up a name. I said, "How's
Steve?" He said, "Believe it or not,
Steve owns seven restaurants."
>> Oh, good for Steve.
>> And I said, "Really?" He said, "We set
him up with one restaurant. He just had
a knack for it and now he has seven
restaurants. He's rich. I said, "Good
for him." So, he made a life for
himself. He said, "Yeah, his kids are in
college. Everything's good." I said,
"Great. That's what it's all about."
>> So, the witness protection thing is is
is a real thing.
>> Oh, it's a real thing.
>> And then he just gets vanishes. And
>> you you get American citizenship.
>> Your family gets American citizenship.
Uh you get the seed money to start
whatever it is you want. I mean, you've
provided us with a great service. And
whatever we negotiated, I'm going to
give him a hundred,000. I'm going to
give him a million or five million or
whatever it's going to be. That's what
he used to get started in life.
>> But those people and that's where the
real talk gets gets in is those people
are are informants against their country
at the end of the day. They've committed
espionage
>> or treason some treason. Right.
>> Mhm.
>> So in that sense, how are they viewed in
the CIA? Are those are they're viewed as
people?
>> Yeah, that's a good question. So,
you would think that they would be held
at arms length because they they're
traitors.
>> Yeah. But there is such an overwhelming
sense in the CIA that we are the good
guys that we consider them to be the
good guys